Guide to the Humanities Council Records RG.9.5.1
New York University Archives
Humanities Council Records
Early 1970s-1996
New York University Archives
New York University. Humanities Council
Berlowitz, Leslie
RG.9.5.1
49 Linear Feet in 82 manuscript boxes, 4 half-manuscript boxes, 7 cassette boxes, 1 record carton, 2 oversize flat boxes, folders in 3 shared oversize flat boxes, and audiocassettes in 1 shared box.
3 VHS
21 Quarter_Inch_Audio_Reel
253 audiocassettes
14.8 Megabytes in 736 computer files
New York University (NYU) formed the Humanities Council in 1976 to offer cross-faculty, interdisciplinary humanities programs in the format of seminars, lectures, colloquia, and other events. Leslie Berlowitz was the Council's director from its creation until she left NYU in 1996, at which point the Council was disbanded. The Humanities Council Records (dated early 1970s-1996) include administrative files, grant applications and reports, and program and project files related to the Council's activities on NYU's campus and in collaboration with other institutions.
Conditions Governing Access
Oral history transcripts in Subseries III.C are restricted for 75 years from their creation date to maintain the privacy of interviewees. All other materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials transferred to the University Archives by Leslie Berlowitz in 1984, 1992, and on other unknown dates. Materials were previously split and assigned two call numbers, RG 9.5.1 and RG 9.5.1.1. In 2024 they were reunited under RG 9.5.1.
Appraisal
Commercially produced bound materials, as well as duplicates of brochures, posters, and reports, were removed from the collection. Student grades from Humanities Council seminars were also removed to protect the privacy of former students.
One floppy disk could not be imaged and was discarded.
Separated Materials
Records created by Leslie Berlowitz in her capacity as Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs have been transferred to RG 9.5, the Records of the Office of Associate Vice President for Academic Affairs (Leslie Berlowitz). Records related to the Faculty Resouce network have been transferred to RG 9.5.5, the Records of the Faculty Resource Network. New York Insitute of Humanities records were transferred to RG 37.4, Records of the New York Institute for the Humanities.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact New York University Archives at special.collections@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Historical Note
New York University created the Humanities Council in 1976 due to concern that college students were eschewing humanities studies in favor of technical and professional education, which was perceived as more valuable in the job market of the time. The Council was preceded by a Presidential Panel on Humanities and primarily aimed to plan humanities-centered, interdisciplinary programming for NYU faculty and students, including promoting humanities studies in NYU's professional schools. Leslie Berlowitz (née Tuttleton, 1944-2020) worked in the Office of Academic Affairs, was a member of the Council from its founding, and headed it until it was disbanded in 1996, at which time she left NYU.
The Humanities Council created interdisciplinary humanities programming for the NYU community, secondary and post-secondary education students in the New York City metro area, and for academics and professionals engaged in humanities work. In 1976, the Council introduced humanities seminars for NYU students, and colloquia for NYU faculty. In the late 1970s it also began planning programming explicitly for students of professional schools, and began sponsoring lectures, conferences, and symposia. Notably, the Council began working with visiting scholars to create the Distinguished Visiting Scholar Lecture Series. In 1979 the Council also began a joint humanities programming project with Rockefeller University. During the 1980s, the Council branched out to developing programming for high school students and educators. Towards the end of the 1980s and into the 1990s, the Council focused on larger, multi-year projects that offered a variety of programming centered around a single topic.
The Humanities Council was initially funded by a 1976 grant from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, and in 1978 received additional funds from the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH). The latter was a challenge grant, which matched funds raised by NYU. The NEH challenge grant was renewed in 1983, when the University executed a fundraising campaign to create an endowment fund for the Council. Over its existence the Council also received funding from the Exxon Education Fund, the Rockefeller Foundation, the Pew Memorial Trust, and other granting institutions. In its first decade, the Council received grants that provided more long-term, general funding, but over the course of time grants became more specific and tied to individual programs. In addition to planning programming directly, the Council also provided funds for seminars, lectures, readings, and other events planned by NYU faculty. It did so primarily through the Grant-in-Aid program, which ran from 1980 to 1992.
Scope and Contents
The Humanities Council Records (dated early 1970s-1996) include materials related to the founding, administration, funding, and programs of the Council. The majority of the collection is paper records, but each series contains electronic records as well as audiovisual materials. Research files on humanities education, committee records, promotional materials, grant applications and reports, and requests for funding from the Humanities Council document the overall planning and administration of the Council. Different types of programming, including seminars, lectures, symposia, conferences, readings, discussion sessions, exhibitions, and tributes, are documented by correspondence with potential participants; promotional materials including brochures, posters, and fliers; mailing lists; event invitations and scripts; and audiovisual recordings. Later projects, which were often planned in concert with events at other institutions, are also represented by correspondence, planning meeting files, calendars, and promotional materials related to events outside of NYU. Overall, the Humanities Council Records document trends in academic humanities studies during its 20 years of existence. Funding documentation, particularly grant proposals and reports, but also visits from and lectures by representatives of public granting institutions, also show changes in the nature of funds available for this type of programming. Files from individual events provide information on specific topics and subjects. The Council consistently devoted resources to humanities education for professional students across all of its programming, and themes related to the bicentennials of the U.S. Constitution and the French Revolution are explored in all aspects of the Humanities Council's activities.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in five series. All series are arranged chronologically. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: Administrative Files, 1976-1996
Series II: NYU Programming, 1976-1995
Series III: Outside Programming, 1977-1993
Series IV: Projects, 1982-1996
Series V: Audiovisual Recordings, 1976-1996
Humanities; Grants.; Lectures.; Colloquiums; Symposia; French Revolution Bicentennial, 1989; Medicine and the Humanities; United States Constitution Bicentennial, 1987-1991; National Endowment for the Humanities; Rockefeller Foundation; Berlowitz, Leslie
- Series I: Administrative Files, early 1970s through 1996; 9.08 Megabytes in 415 computer files; 11 Linear Feet in 19 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize flat box, and 2 folders in additional oversize flat boxes; 4 audiocassettes
  Scope and Contents
  Series I: Administrative Files (dated early 1970s-1996) includes files documenting the activities of the Humanities Council as a whole. It includes records regarding the organization and membership of the council, including agendas and meeting minutes of the Council, its Executive Board, and all subordinate committees, subcommittees. It also includes grant proposals, correspondence, and files documenting requests for and grants of funding. Records of the Graduate Student Forum, a program conceived to enhance the professional development of humanities graduate students, and materials documenting other fellowships, assistantships, and professional development activities planned for different parts of the NYU community are also included. The majority of this series is paper records, but some files also contain electronic records. This series also includes audio recordings from two events: a Graduate Student Forum event and a reception for National Endowment for the Humanities Chair Lynne Cheney.
  Arrangement
  This series has been arranged into seven subseries. Files are arranged chronologically within subseries. The subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
  Subseries I.A Founding and Dissolution Records, 1976-1996
  Subseries I.B Committees, 1976-1992
  Subseries I.C Funding, Budgets, and Expenses, 1976-1995
  Subseries I.D Reports and Publications, 1976-1989
  Subseries I.E Programs and Events, 1976-1992
  Subseries I.F Medical and Dental Humanities, 1977-1991
  Subseries I.G Publicity and Communications, 1979-1992
  - Subseries I.A: Founding and Dissolution, circa early 1970s to 1996; 2 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes
    Subseries I.A Founding and Dissolution (dated early 1970s-1996) primarily contains files related to the early years of the Humanities Council, with one file about winding down Council activities. The founding documents include files from the Presidential Panel on Humanities, the predecessor to the Council, Council organizational charts, and research files about humanities education generally and humanities programs at other universities.
    - Presidential Panel on Humanities, circa early 1970s (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Humanities Council Reorganization, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Research Files, 1979-1981 (Box 9, Folder 8-10)
    - News Clippings about Humanities, 1979-1983 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Humanities Council Winddown, 1995-1996 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Subseries I.B: Committees, 1976-1992; 3 Linear Feet in 6 manuscript boxes; 5.9 Megabytes in 52 computer files
    Subseries I.B Committees (dated 1976-1990) documents the activities of the full Humanities Council, its Executive Board, and topical committees and subcommittees that were part of the Council. The documents are primarily paper, with a minority of electronic records, and include agendas, minutes, and documents circulated to committee members. This subseries also includes committee rosters.
    - Full Council Meetings, 1976-1992
      - Paper Records, 1976-1977, 1983-1990
        - 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
        - 1983-1985 (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
        - 1985-1990 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
      - Electronic Records, 1984-1992; RG_9-5-1_ER_14
    - Executive Board, 1976-1991
      - Paper Records, 1976-1985, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4-9, Box 3, Folder 1-4)
      - Electronic Records, 1983-1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_10
    - Ad-Hoc Committee of Humanities Departments Group, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Colloquia Subcommittee, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Subcommittee on Development, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Subcommittee on Research, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Seminars Subcommittee, 1976-1980 (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Committee and Subcommittee Membership, 1976-1985
      - Paper Records, 1976-1985 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Electronic Records, 1976-1985; RG_9-5-1_ER_4
    - Lectures and Faculty Development Subcommittee, 1976-1989
      - Paper Records, 1976-1989 (Box 17, Folder 1-6)
      - Electronic Records, 1983-1987; RG_9-5-1_ER_23
    - Faculty-Related Activities Committee, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Curriculum Development and Networking Subcommittee, 1977-1989
      - Paper Records, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
      - Electronic Records, 1980-1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_7
    - Subcommittee on Graduate Education, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
    - Professional School Outreach Subcommittee, 1983-1990
      - Paper Records, 1983-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
      - Electronic Records, 1983; RG_9-5-1_ER_19
    - TV Education Working Group, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Graduate Committee, 1987-1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_16
    - Humanities Council Advisory Group, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries I.C: Funding, Budgets, and Expenses, 1976-1995; 4.5 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes and 1 folder in an oversize flat box; 398.6 kilobytes in 162 computer files
    Subseries I.C Funding, Budgets, and Expenses (dated 1976-1995) contains records of the Humanities Council's finances. The Council relied on outside funding sources, and this subseries includes drafts and copies of grant proposals and reports, as well as correspondence between the Council and the granting institutions. It also includes other records related to Council fundraising, including research files on and correspondence with potential funders and records related to the Council's plan to build an endowment fund. Additionally, the Humanities Council itself provided funds for humanities programming at NYU. The Council ran a small grants program, Grant-in-Aid, which is represented with applications for funds and Council responses. The Council also issued calls for funding requests and received requests outside of the Grant-in-Aid program, which are included in this subseries.
    - Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, 1976-1989
      - Interim Report, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 10)
      - Reports, 1984-1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_25
      - Mailing List, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Funding Requests, 1977-1995
      - Paper Records, 1977-1995 (Box 8, Folder 1-23)
      - Electronic Records, 1983; RG_9-5-1_ER_15
    - Humanities Council Request for Funding, 1977-1979 (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
    - The Samuel and May Rudin Foundation, 1981-1990
      - Paper Records, 1981-1990 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Electronic Records, 1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_30
    - Samuel Rudin Professorship in the Humanities, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Grant-in-Aid, 1980-1992
      - Paper Records, 1980-1990 (Box 14, Folder 1-9, Box 15, Folder 1-7)
      - Electronic Records, 1983-1992; RG_9-5-1_ER_18
    - Endowment Project, 1982-1984 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Call for Funding Requests, 1983-1984 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Potential Funding Sources, 1983-1984, undated
      - List of Foundations, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Arthur Vining Davis Foundation, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Harry F. Guggenheim Foundation, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Surdna Foundation, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Lilly Endowment, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Soros Foundation, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Pew Charitible Trusts, 1983-1986
      - Pew Foundation Background Materials and Drafts, 1983-1984
        - Paper Records, 1983-1984 (Box 20, Folder 1)
        - Electronic Records, 1983; RG_9-5-1_ER_28
      - Final Proposal, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Report, 1984-1986 (Box 20, Folder 3-5)
    - National Endowment for the Humanitites, 1983-1993
      - Challenge Grant, 1983-1993
        - Background Materials and Drafts, 1983
          - Paper Records, Spring 1983 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
          - Electronic Records, Spring 1983; RG_9-5-1_ER_26
        - Proposal Narrative, Spring 1983 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
        - Final Proposal, June 1983 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
        - One Million Dollar Special Fund, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - Challenge Grant Program Information, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - Preliminary Proposal and Early Drafts, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 5-6)
        - Application, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 7-8, Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Research Conference Grant Proposal, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Exxon Education Fund Grant Report, 1984-1988
      - Paper Records, 1986-1988 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Electronic Records, 1984; RG_9-5-1_ER_12
    - Humanities Council Expenses, 1984-1994
      - Paper Records, 1984, 1992-1994 (Box Shared University Archives 155, Folder 3, Box 7, Folder 7-8)
      - Electronic Records, 1989-1992; RG_9-5-1_ER_11
    - Ford Foundation, 1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_13
    - Budgets, 1989-1996
      - Electronic Records, 1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_6
      - Paper Records, 1995-1996 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - The Samuel Bronfman Foundation, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Subseries I.D: Reports and Publications, 1976-1989; 2.75 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box; 2.03 Megabytes in 103 computer files
    Subseries I.D Reports and Publications (dated 1976-1989) contains Humanities Council annual reports and other reports compiled for University administration. This subseries also includes various publications produced by the Council, including program guidelines and informational booklets. The Humanities Council also published "Highlights," which provided lists of humanities-related events in poster format, and these posters are included in this subseries. This series is primarily made up of paper materials, but also includes born-digital drafts of some reports and publications.
    - "Highlights", 1976-1994
      - Paper Records, 1976-1994 (Box 89, Folder 3-13)
      - Electronic Records, 1976-1994; RG_9-5-1_ER_1
    - Humanities Booklet, 1977-1980 (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
    - Reports to NYU Administration, 1977-1989
      - Paper Records, 1977-1989 (Box 9, Folder 4-7, Box 20, Folder 6-8)
      - Electronic Records, 1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_29
    - Undergraduate Humanities Journal, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Briefing Books, 1980-1982 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Annual Reports, 1982-1989
      - Paper Records, 1982-1989 (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Electronic Records, 1982-1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_2
    - Guidelines, 1983-1986
      - Paper Records, 1983-1986 (Box 18, Folder 5-7)
      - Electronic Records, 1983-1986; RG_9-5-1_ER_21
  - Subseries I.E: Programs and Events, 1976-1992; 5.75 Linear Feet in 11 manuscript boxes and 1 half-manuscript box; 4 audiocassettes; 532 kilobytes in 43 computer files
    Subseries I.E Programs and Events (dated 1976-1992) contains records evidencing Humanities Council-wide events and programs. Events documents include correspondence, invitations, mailing lists, and records related to logistical matters such as catering and hotel arrangements. The Council hosted some visitors who were political and governmental figures, and individual files are present for the visits of French President François Mitterand, King Juan Carlos I of Spain, the Duke of Alba, and National Endowment for the Humanities Chair Lynne Cheney. This subseries also contains documents about council-sponsored fellowships, assistantships, and professional development programs. From 1984 to 1992, the Council organized the Graduate Student Forum, which held meetings and provided financial support for graduate student research and conference attendance. The Graduate Student Forum was funded by the Samuel and May Rudin Foundation, and this subseries includes reports to the Foundaton, planning files for GSF events. This series also includes audio recordings of a lecture at a Graduate Student Forum event, Lynne Cheney's remarks during her visit, and event photographs.
    - Humanities Council Preceptor Program, 1976-1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Nominations for Assistantships, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Program Proposals, 1977-1981, 1990, 1995
      - Paper Records, 1977-1981, 1990, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 2-11)
      - Electronic Records, 1990; RG_9-5-1_ER_3
    - Humanities Research Development Day, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Lists of Events, 1978-1994
      - Paper Records, 1978-1994 (Box 6, Folder 12-14)
      - Electronic Records, 1980-1994; RG_9-5-1_ER_9
    - Receptions and Parties, 1979, 1983, 1986, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Distinguished Visitor Planning Files, 1981-1993
      - President François Mitterand, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - King Juan Carlos I of Spain, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Duke of Alba, 1984; RG_9-5-1_ER_8
      - National Endowment for the Humanities Chair Lynne Cheney, 1987
        - Dinner, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 2-3, Box 88, Folder 15)
        - "A Dialogue with NYU Faculty", March 16, 1987 (Box 94, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0092)
        - News Clippings, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Hotel Research, 1988-1991 (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
      - Interpreters, 1988 (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Catering, circa 1990s (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - NYU Trolley, 1993 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Photographs and Contact Sheets, 1982-1986 (Box 19, Folder 1-12)
    - Mellon Humanities Network, 1983-1984; RG_9-5-1_ER_81
    - Humanities Council Fellows, 1984 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Graduate Student Forum, 1984-1992
      - Reports to Rudin Foundation, 1984-1992 (Box 15, Folder 8, Box 16, Folder 1-3)
      - Events, 1984-1991 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Galway Kinnell and Aileen Ward--"Poetry and Technology", November 18, 1985
        - Audio -- 1 of 2 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0136)
        - Audio -- 2 of 2 (Box 92, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0137)
      - Member Lists, 1985-1992 (Box 16, Folder 6)
      - Letters from Participants, 1986 (Box 16, Folder 8-9)
      - Planning Meetings, 1988-1992 (Box 16, Folder 4-5)
      - Correspondence with Rudin Foundation, 1984-1990
        - Electronic Records, 1984-1990; RG_9-5-1_ER_17
        - Paper Records, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Humanities Council 10th Anniversary, 1985-1986
      - Paper Records, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Electronic Records, 1986; RG_9-5-1_ER_20
    - Event Attendance Lists, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Rockefeller Foundation Humanities Fellowship, 1989
      - Paper Records, 1989 (Box 55, Folder 6)
      - Electronic Records, 1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_87
    - National Book Critics Circle Awards, 1989-1995
      - Paper Records, 1989-1995 (Box 86, Folder 5)
      - Audio Recording, March 8, 1990 (Box Shared University Archives 151, Audiocassette 9-5-1.0290)
  - Subseries I.F: Medical and Dental Humanities, 1977-1991; 2 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes and 2 folders in oversize flat boxes; 28.9 kilobytes in 4 computer files
    Subseries I.F Medical and Dental Humanities (dated 1977-1992) comprises records demonstrating the Humanities Council's efforts to reach out to NYU's medical and dental schools and records created during the planning and administration of these programs. The subseries includes program proposals and reports, correspondence with NYU's medical and dental community members, and expense reports. Also included is one poster advertising Humanities Council programming and another poster created for the Dental School's 125th anniversary.
    - Proposal to the Dental School, 1977-1980 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Planning Files, 1980-1989
      - Paper Records, 1980-1981, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 21-22)
      - Electronic Records, 1984-1989; RG_9-5-1_ER_22
    - Poster, 1981 (Box 89, Folder 1)